so many of those guys were innocent of
any crimes and to lose eight ten twelve
years of your life for nothing is
inexcusable and a real shame is that our
government doesn't even issue an apology
I'm going to meet John Kiriakou who's a
former CIA case officer he just got out
of prison after spending two years in a
federal penitentiary and he's the only
person who's been prosecuted in
connection with the CIA's enhanced
interrogation program not for
participating in it but for revealing
classified details about it in 2007 John
Kerry aku became the first CIA officer
to reveal that al-qaeda facilitator Abu
Zubaydah was waterboarded a detail that
was then a closely guarded secret
zubeida was the CIA's high-value
detainee captured after 9/11 and the
guinea-pig for the agency's enhanced
interrogation program he's been held
captive at Guantanamo since 2006
waterboarding was one of the techniques
and was it used on Zubaydah it was and
wasn't successful
it was the unauthorized disclosure to
ABC News turned Kiriakou into a
household name overnight led to a
lucrative book deal and landed him on
the government's radar after he told ABC
News that Abu Zubaydah was tortured
Kiriakou revealed another piece of
classified information to a journalist
the identity of a covert CIA operative
who was involved in the CIA's rendition
detention and interrogation program the
government prosecuted Kuryakin for the
week and in 2013 he accepted a plea deal
that sent him away to a federal
penitentiary for two and a half years we
caught up with Kuryakin at his home in
Arlington Virginia just a few days after
he was released
hey how are you good to see you good to
see you please come in thank you good to
be home
yeah it's good to be home it's
frustrating too at the same time
you know I was only gone 23 months and
the adjustment the readjustment is thank
you thank you it's dramatic these guys
who do 10 20 30 years I don't know how
they readjust and I can see why people
don't want to leave prison after all in
addition to a broken chair that I sit in
every day I've got a job situation where
I've got to work 40 hours a week from an
approved office or store or business or
whatever not from home okay or I risk
going back to prison and I didn't know
that until last night so I've accepted
this terrific job working from home in
business development for a medical
technology company and they told me last
night either get an office or quit and
then if I don't get a 40-hour job I risk
going back to prison I posted this on
Twitter this morning it says I really
need a job must be 40 hours and not from
home I don't want the halfway house to
send me back to prison just for
unemployment ideas John you got to admit
your resume is a little unorthodox my
resume is unorthodox warburg I'm CIA
trained spy right former spy right on
the Abu Zubaydah capture team spent two
years in federal prison yes yes what
skill set are you gonna lie in the real
world I count the current Secretary of
State among my former employers yeah and
I'm gonna end up at a Dunkin Donuts so
that's the world I'm living in right now
esoteric taste in literature yeah
my country versus video like when Holly
I wanted something sympathetic on these
long bus rides up to the what was your
first day out like I was originally told
I would spend an hour at the halfway
house and then be sent home on house
arrest so
my wife and kids and a friend picked me
up at prison and we were gonna stop for
lunch but decided not to risk it we were
afraid we didn't have enough time first
meal when you got out you did that whole
you know weed or something you have been
like craving yeah I was craving Greek
food and we planned it out that we would
stop for lunch at a friend's diner here
in Arlington I was gonna get a gyro
platter and that just didn't happen so
that night what do we eat that night my
wife cooked that night and then the next
night we we ordered out sushi yeah
things you were again to do prison
that's right oh the prison in prison
it's an all carb all the time diet right
yeah like everybody I put on weight in
prison I actually had a lot of trouble
sleeping that first night you know it's
funny you get you get used to this steel
slab with a thin mattress on on the top
and you get used to the sound of keys
jangling all night long as the
corrections officers walk through your
your cell counting people and and it's
so quiet here it's so quiet and prison
is so incredibly loud in part because
it's so incredibly overcrowded I mean
this is federal prison yeah you're in
there with you know some of the worst of
the worst oh yeah yeah this is this is a
common misnomer
this was no Club fed this was no you
know camp with the three hole golf
course and this was real prison
honest-to-god prison with walls and
concertina wire and you know the whole
thing that you see on MSNBC at 11
o'clock at night in terms of
survivability did you like fall back on
your training oh yeah did you use your
your Co skills in fact in fact I've
written the first draft of a book called
doing time like a spy how the CIA taught
me to survive and thrive in prison so
you wrote this by hand in prison yeah no
access computer no access to even a
typewriter what I did is I relied almost
solely on my CIA training I made
strategic alliances for
example from the minute I got there and
there was some serendipity involved too
I was a little nervous because I wasn't
sure you know what I should do where I
should go where I should sit so I kept
to myself the first couple of days and I
allowed people to come up to me and so I
ended up becoming most friendly with the
Italians and I don't mean just people
with Italian names I mean the Italians
and you know all five families were
represented there as well as northern
New Jersey and New England and we hit it
off famously I was in prison about a
week when Louis Farrakhan made a very
supportive statement and so that made me
good with the Muslims so in terms of
like the racial politics that helped you
it helped me greatly most Muslims in
prison are not necessarily religious
Muslims Muslims in prison are more of a
gang than a religious group so that's
sort of guaranteed that that expression
of support from Farrakhan sort of
guaranteed no problems for me on that
front because I was not a rat or a child
molester I was embraced by the Aryans
went to the Aryan Super Bowl party went
to the Aryan Christmas party sat at the
Aryan table for the first year until I
moved in with the Italians and so you
know I formed these strategic alliances
that really made the time much easier
than it otherwise could have been
there's only one group that that I
actively ostracized and stayed away from
and that was the child molesters
nobody associates with the child
molesters except other child molesters
and and I kept away
the government alleged that Kuryakin was
a prolific leaker disclosing classified
information to journalists about the
CIA's enhanced interrogation program on
numerous occasions between 2007 and 2009
do you ever just think like this is
crazy
like I helped capture like some of the
top suspects in the global war on terror
and now I have to report to a parole
officer
what what's crazy to me is what my
attorneys initially described to me as
selective and vindictive prosecution
that's an actual legal term and there
are supposedly laws to protect people
from being the subject of vindictive and
selective prosecutions my attorneys
believed and I believed that I was a
victim of a selective and vindictive
prosecution I think that the Justice
Department has been incredibly
hypocritical in leaked cases I mean
Washington operates on leaks and the
truth of the matter has turned out to be
if if it's a supporter of the president
leaking or the leak makes the government
look good you're good to go if your leak
is critical of the government or the
government wants to punish you in some
way then they prosecute you well the
last three directors of the Central
Intelligence Agency have leaked
prolifically and in one case Leon
Panetta former DCI Leon Panetta did
exactly the same thing I did where he he
outed the Navy SEAL that led the bin
Laden raid but he said oh my bad it was
a it was an accident and he's free to
you know cash his six million dollar
book advance well you know I'm
prosecuted to go to prison and lose my
pension and everything
can I offer you guys a cup of coffee
sure that'd be great it's decaf is that
Alright John can you talk me through
what was happening in Pakistan in in
2001 and 2002 were sure I was working
from headquarters on September 11th and
and my god I wanted to avenge like
everybody I wanted to avenge the the
9/11 attacks so so I volunteered to go
overseas in the days when our official
relationship with the Pakistanis was
very close it was very close very warm
very cooperative we did a lot of good
work together and I came to really like
and respect my my Pakistani counterparts
after the fall of Tora Bora most most al
Qaeda fighters that had been in
Afghanistan had fled to Pakistan so our
job was to figure out where they were
hiding and to try to capture them well
when I first arrived my my boss told me
to come up with a plan to take down al
Qaeda safehouse I had never I had had
training of course but I had never but
actually taken down the safehouse I came
up with this plan we had an informant
who slipped us an address of a suspected
safehouse and just to try it out we hit
it at two o'clock in the morning and we
caught some Egyptian Islamic Jihad guy
hide now and he had escaped from
Afghanistan so we said hey you know we
had some success we tried it again a
week later we caught a couple of
Tunisian teenagers who had gone through
the training in Afghanistan and had
slipped into Pakistan so this was a
workable formula we got word from
Washington that Abu Zubaydah was
somewhere in Pakistan and our job was to
catch him at the time we thought that
Abu Zubaydah was a major on Qaeda figure
turned out he was not he was never an
actual member of al-qaeda
he had never pledged fealty to Osama bin
Laden but he was the commander of
two training camps and we hadn't
captured any major al-qaeda leaders we
had only killed one we had killed
Mohammed Atta on a bombing in Tora Bora
so we went after Abu Zubaydah we were
able to get it down to 14 different
sites the day before the actual
operation we went to each one of these
14 sites and just coincidentally we got
to one site that we thought was probably
gonna be a big deal for us and my phone
rang and it was the analyst and he said
that Abu Zubaydah had made a mistake in
his communications I probably shouldn't
say more than that on that point and
then at 2:00 a.m. we beat down the door
of all 14 places the Abu Zubaydah house
it turned out how to steel reinforced
door and so it took quite some time many
minutes to get through the door by the
time we got through the door I was a
beta a Syrian bomber and Abu Zubaydah's
bodyguard had made it to the roof of the
house and they were jumping to the roof
of the next house to try to escape and a
Pakistani soldier shot all three of them
as they came down or as they jumped and
then they came down after being hit the
syrian was killed instantly
Abu Zubaydah was gravely wounded he was
shot in the thigh the groin and the
stomach with an ak-47 and then the
bodyguard was shot through the leg and
and that's how we got him zu beta was
then whisked away to a CIA black site
prison in Thailand where he became the
first high-value detainee subjected to
the so-called enhanced interrogation
techniques your job was to capture yeah
my job was to capture a plane would
invariably fly in from where I don't
know to where I don't know and we would
load them on the plane and and never see
them again the agency had no training
program in interrogation we had never
done interrogations but
and interrogations we learned the hard
way are something that you just can't
you can't wing you you have to be
trained that's why the FBI over the
years has been so much more successful
believe me I hate criticize the
complimenting rather the FBI but they're
really good at what they do and and the
CIA wasn't at least not in 2002 and so
they made a lot of mistakes I know that
you have been an outspoken advocate
against torture and the enhanced
interrogation techniques even before you
went to prison
now having actually been incarcerated
and been a prisoner yourself has it
changed your perspective at all is it
deep into your resolve its deep in my
resolve and it's also exposed to me what
a problem prison conditions are and how
necessary prison reform is in this
country we should be ashamed of
ourselves for the state of our prisons
we really need to learn from our
European allies how to incarcerate
people what do you do next how do you
pick up the pieces you're a felon right
yeah I'm a convicted felon so I lost my
pension I can't vote I'm under the
control of Bureau of Prisons for the
next three years I'd like to eventually
end up at a think-tank I'd like to write
and speak and teach maybe do some TV
news commentary like I did before I was
arrested but I think it's gonna take a
little bit of time kiriakos job fears
were never borne out not long after our
interview the halfway house relented and
said he could work for the medical
technology company from home and it
doesn't look like he'll have to wait too
long to hook up with a think-tank
kyriaki told us he accepted a job as an
associate fellow with the Institute of
policy studies where he will cover
torture intelligence policy the Middle
East
and prison reform
[Music]
[Laughter]